Okay, so welcome everybody. Thank you for coming on Easter. I'm coming in then.
Today we've got the
lovely Amy from the Luna Cystic Collective coming to talk to us about cyclical
living.
So we're really excited about this one. Obviously we do so many things, don't
we, about
womanhood and connecting to ourselves and all that jazz. So we're really
excited for this.
We've been looking forward to this for a while. So this is something I've been
wanting to learn
about for so long and I think it's very important that we all learn about
because
I feel different things when I'm going through my cycle and I don't really know
what it means
or how to explain it. So it's really nice that we've got you to come and
educate us on it.
So thank you for coming along. It's very important to think for all of us
because we don't get taught
this. We don't get taught it at all. Yeah, I'm with you on that one because I
went to a girl school
and literally did not even cover it. It's just like, if I don't give you a very
important number,
so hopefully it'll be a bit more interesting than that tonight and dive into it
a little bit more
and give you some kind of pointers to get really started on living more in tune
with your cycle
hopefully. Amazing. Thank you. Well, I think George and I have been talking
about this for a while
so I'm kind of like self-taught as in I know nothing apart from what means I've
seen on the
internet but I try and like track my cycle and do things according to it so it
'd be good to actually
to actually go. So I'm going to make you the host now. Hey, there we go. Cool.
All right.
All right, so I'm going to share my screen with you guys so just bear with me
one second. I don't know how long we have been in the Zoom world but I'm still
not quite used to it.
So hello everyone. My name is Amy and I am the founder of Lunasistic Collective
. So Lunasistic
Collective is an online platform basically and it's all about living more in
tune with your cycle
or just with the natural cycle. So when I say the natural cycles we have kind
of three main ones.
We've got the seasons of the year so winter, spring, summer, autumn. We've got
the cycle,
the phases of the moon and then we've also obviously got the menstrual cycle.
So I'm going to be focusing
more on the menstrual cycle here this evening. On Lunasistic Collective we have
a bunch of free
content so it kind of started off life as a blog where I was just wanting to
explore a bit more.
I couldn't find anywhere on the internet like it so I wanted to create this
kind of nice online
community where people could come and read about supportive information for
supporting each phase
of their menstrual cycle whether it's through Ayurveda or yoga or diet,
exercise, anything like
that. More of a holistic look at the menstrual cycle and then I started to get
a little bit
more interested in the moon and what was going on with that and kind of the
seasons and stuff
and now it's kind of blossomed into more of an online membership as well. So we
have a membership
area where we've got a lot of mindful content. So we've got videos on yoga,
mindful practices,
meditation, all of that stuff, all about supporting you at each section of your
menstrual cycle, each phase of your menstrual cycle so that you can really kind
of tune in
your self-care practices to be more in alignment with your body. So that's a
little bit about me
and what I do. I'll probably be talking a little bit more about Lunasistic
Collective as we go along.
But before we kick things off I just wanted to really dive in to your
relationship with your
menstrual cycle. So if you've got a pen and paper with you that can be handy
otherwise maybe if
you've got your notes on your phone or something but just taking a couple of
minutes here to just
have a little think about how you currently feel about your menstrual cycle. Is
it positive? Is it
negative? Do you not really care? Do you not really think about it? Just jot
ting a few thoughts down.
No wrong answers at all. Just having a little think about how you feel about
your menstrual cycle really.
And how in tune you feel with your body.
And perhaps considering how you would like to feel about your menstrual cycle.
I can't promise anything tonight but hopefully I'll give you the tools
to be a little bit more positive to meet us.
So I'll just give you a couple more moments on that one. You can always come
back to it later
if you want to see. So from here dive into kind of my why are we here. So it
kind of really
makes me mad and we kind of touched upon it at the beginning there that we're
not really talked
about this in schools. It's kind of very much neglected really. You see all
these kind of
period adverts on the TV where you just kind of suck on a pad and put on your
tiny little
white tennis shorts and go and play a game of tennis and just completely ignore
the idea that
your menstrual period has arrived and it makes me really angry because there's
so many things
going on during the whole cycle of our menstrual cycle and we just ignore it
even in kind of terms
of science and research for so long and a lot of the diets and a lot of like
the nutrition
information that you see in kind of the mainstream media. All of these have
been based upon results
that come from men and for so long women have been treated as little men but we
're really not.
We've got a completely different system going on in our bodies and when you
look at other studies
that are coming out about the menstrual cycle for instance there was one a few
years ago now
but it showed that the brain our brains can actually change up to 25% during
our monthly cycle
in terms of kind of which parts of the brain are working better at different
parts of the cycle.
So our communication systems our memory systems all of that going on and so
there's a lot going on
because we have these hormonal receptors all over our body and because the
menstrual cycle changes
so much our hormonal cycle changes so much throughout the month it really
affects everything
that's going on in our body and as we know well as we're beginning to realise
we are very much
still living in a man's world and the world has not been designed with women's
bodies in mind so
a lot of us I find a lot of women come to me saying that they feel kind of
stressed but out
because they're trying to live up to this expectation that you have to turn up
every day
being and performing at your very best day in day out that very kind of I don't
know
circadian kind of rhythm that kind of nine to five idea where you have to
perform and be at your
very best every single day and a lot of women they struggle with that because
our hormonal systems
just doesn't allow for it so I hope this evening I kind of give you the tools
to help you plan your
life a little bit better so that you're working with your menstrual cycle
rather than against it
so that you can kind of plan your self-care practices you can plan your work
life balance
you can plan your social schedule or more in alignment with your body so that
you're working
with your body rather than against it so when we are looking at the differences
between men and
women I always like to start here by saying that men are like the sun and so
men operate pretty
much on this kind of 24 hour schedule much like the sun so if you look at this
graph here on the
right it shows kind of the the rhythm of testosterone which is kind of one of
the main hormones that
fuels men basically for making it really simple but if we look at it in that
kind of basic sense so
if you see here at eight o'clock in the morning testosterone in men is at its
highest this is when
it's peaking and then throughout the day it gradually drops getting lower and
lower in the
afternoon quite a nice low level this is when men are typically becoming a
little bit more sociable
a little bit more friendly a little bit more amenable and then as the day
progresses on towards the
evening time this is when testosterone levels are at their lowest so men's
energy levels are
typically at their lowest as well this is the time when they typically just
kind of flop in front of
the TV and not do an awful lot and then overnight while they're sleeping their
testosterone levels
rise all the way up again ready to start again the next day same day and day
out 24/7 throughout the
whole year and as you can see kind of our world that we live in the society
that we live in is
very much geared around this system of men so we kind of expected to go to work
in the morning
probably do those those really intense focus tasks first thing in the morning
when typically a man
would be very uber focused on whatever he's doing then in the afternoon we
probably be typically
more having kind of meetings and stuff when there's that lower level of
testosterone men are generally
a little bit more friendly and then in the evening this is when we're expected
to have our downtime
and chill out and it really does follow this kind of rhythm of testosterone
that men have this very
much this 24 hour cycle but unfortunately that just doesn't work for our female
bodies so
women on the other hand are much more like the moon so the moon for those of
you who don't know
the moon moves through kind of typically a 28 day cycle and similar to women
women also move through
typically 28 to 32 days depending on where you are but we're very much like the
moon in this
respect whereas we have this cycle it's not the same no two days are the same
and you can see here
kind of our hormones that fluctuate throughout the month and they're wildly
different on a day-to-day
basis so you've got your day of the cycle here down towards the bottom of the
graph and then up
here you've got your kind of hormone levels so you can see that they change an
awful lot throughout
the month and as I mentioned just a moment ago we have hormone receptors
literally all over our
body and it impacts so much so our hormones can influence the brain power our
energy levels how
strong we're feeling how prone we are to injury our metabolism our appetite
even who we find
attractive changes throughout the course of our cycle as well which is really
quite interesting
so there's a lot going on and we are trying to fit this kind of 28 day cycle we
're expected to fit
it into a 24 hour day and as a result because we're expected to show up the
same day in day out
it just doesn't work for us we end up feeling tired but now we often feel a lot
of guilt because
we're not performing or we don't feel like we're performing at our best every
day and it just
doesn't work for us so we're much more cyclical as as beings and we're much
kind of if we live
more in tune with our cycle we can begin to alleviate these feelings of stress
of burnout we can begin
to live more in tune with our hormones more in tune with our body so that we
just generally feel better
so looking at the cycles in a little bit more detail as I mentioned at the
beginning here we
have typically three main cycles so we have the seasons the moon and the
menstrual cycle and we
can kind of align each different phase of these three cycles together in terms
of energy which
probably doesn't make an awful lot of sense now but I hope become clearer as I
talk more through
it here so we typically say that winter new moon and menstruation are very
similar in their energy
in their nature so when you think about winter you're kind of thinking about
that very quiet
cold dark time of year we're very introverted we want to be inside we don't
want to be doing an
awful lot we want to be eating nice warming foods all that kind of lovely cozy
vibes very similar
to the energy that we see around the time of the new moon so the new moon is
when the moon is
like it's darkest in the sky you probably can't really see it in the sky so the
energy again is
very low it's very quiet it's very introverted way back when our ancestors were
living in caves
and what have you we probably wouldn't have been out hunting or anything
because there's no there's
no light we can't see that well so we're more vulnerable to being um prayed
upon so we're more
likely to be staying inside and just really being inside the cozy and warm very
similar to the
energy at menstruation so menstruation is when our hormone levels are at their
lowest so as a result
our energy feels pretty low as well we feel pretty tired around this time again
feeling pretty
introverted don't really want to be going out doing an awful lot socializing
just doesn't feel
that great and if we do we probably end up feeling a little bit more burnt out
throughout the rest
of our cycle just because we gave too much of ourselves away during our
menstrual time when we
should have been resting and preparing for the cycle ahead so then we move into
spring and when
we think about spring we think about kind of new beginnings creativity play
fulness it's that kind
of energy very similar to the waxing moon where the light of the moon is
growing in the sky is
getting bigger and bold and again very similar to our follicular phase so our
follicular phase is
that time just after our period where our hormone levels are beginning to rise
again we're perhaps
feeling a little bit more creative a little bit more playful and a bit more
ready to be out there
in the wild again then we come around to summer so summer the energy is high we
're at our best
really we're extroverted we're socializing we want to be outside we want to be
seeing people very
similar to the energy of the full moon where the moon is at its brightest in
the sky and lots of
things gone in in the natural world around the time of the full moon as well so
a lot of fish
kind of plan that they're breeding in time with the full moon corals spawn and
release their eggs
at the time of the full moon and there's been a lot of studies done in human
behaviour as well
I know personally that I feel almost a little bit overwhelmed with the energy
when the full moon
rolls around I find it more difficult to sleep and I was actually reading today
that there was a study
that showed that people typically it takes them longer to fall to sleep on a
full moon and they
also sleep for a less amount of time so obviously a lot going on around that
time and it's very similar
to the energy that we experienced during ovulation so ovulation is when our
hormone levels are at
their highest and it's also our fertile window so we're probably feeling pretty
pretty down good
with we're feeling quite vocal quite social and flirty sexy all of that kind of
really
fun energy is going on at full pelt or ovulation this is when you'll be feeling
your best
and then from summer we move into autumn so autumn vibes kind of thinking about
harvesting
slowing down not starting anything new really kind of tying up please sense
that kind of energy
very similar to the waning moon again we've gone from that full moon and the
moon is starting to
shrink back down once more in the sky so that kind of that drop in energy very
similar to the luteal
phase which we see in the menstrual cycle which is when once again the hormonal
levels are dropping
once more so we're starting to feel a little bit more introverted again so
those are kind of the
cycles the phases of the cycle sorry and we're going to dive into each one in a
little bit more
detail now so that you can really begin to see how you can plan your schedule
around your menstrual
cycle when what is going on in your body so I will say that um a lot of this I
've tried to kind of
weave my experience of my menstrual cycle alongside a little bit of science as
well um but the science
is a little bit patchy it's still quite new it's in its infancy um as I
mentioned before a lot of
research has typically kind of cancelled menstruating women out because it's
kind of always been too
difficult to measure um what the scientist is testing with a menstruating woman
because the hormones
they fluctuate too much so they never know if the outcome of their research is
because of what
they were testing or if it was because of the fluctuating hormone levels so
research is patchy
but I've done my best to kind of dig around and see what I can find for you
guys this evening
so we're going to start with your inner winter or mence duration and as I
mentioned this is when
our hormones are at the lowest level so I'm generally talking about oestrogen
and progesterone
mainly here and with this drop in our hormone levels our energy is generally
pretty low at this time
so it's a very introverted time we're not thinking we're not thinking about
going out and socializing
too much we're very much in ourselves we're in our own little bubble we're in
our own little world
but it's a really good time because intuition is at its highest here so because
of these low levels
of hormones the two sides of our brain this is when they're communicating at
their very best so we have
the left side of our brain which is our analytical mind and then our right side
of our brain is our
feeling mind so this is when they're communicating the best between two of the
sides both of the sides
so it's a time for considering if what is really happening in your life is
really working for you
whether it's your work whether it's projects that you've had going on you might
think about
what you've had going on in the previous weeks whether it worked for you taking
that time to
reflect on what worked what didn't and planning for the future how you want
your life to go
so as I say it could be in terms of your work your projects that you've got
going on
or it might be in your personal life it might be a relationship that you're in
a friendship that
you have anything like that where you really need to think clearly if it's what
you want if it's
working for you this is the time to think about it get your journal out start
writing down notes
about how you're feeling what you're thinking at this time and if you're not
sure that's fine
take a few cycles and what you if you see patterns that keep coming up it's a
sure sign that it's time
to either move forwards with it or move away from it you'll know in yourself
what is right for you
so it's a really good time for that kind of clarity we're not starting anything
new we're
really reflecting on on what's going on in our lives at this moment what it's
not a good time
for during our menstruation is being super busy or being quite intense in our
in our workout schedule
so take the time to rest and replenish here as I mentioned our hormones are at
their lowest levels
and it seems kind of the research is still fairly new and a little bit patchy
but it seems that
oestrogen has a protective effect on our muscles and this is when oestrogen as I
mentioned is at
its lowest levels and certain studies have showed that women who men who
exercise around their
menstruation are more likely to injure themselves and their recovery after
exercise is so much more
longer than what it is at other phases in their cycles so they're more likely
to experience that
kind of delayed onset muscle soreness and that kind of painfulness after after
exercising if
they exercise during menstruation and it's also a time for kind of um your fat
storage gets turned
on much more during an exercise here as well because you're putting your body
under stress and it's
thinking why are you doing this to me it doesn't like it at all and rather than
kind of building
muscle or anything like that it kind of turns on its stress response which is I
guess not really
what you're looking for when you're working out and it's also been found that
you put more stress on
your cardiovascular system if you exercise during your period so for me I
typically like to treat the
first few days of my cycle my period as a little bit of a holiday in terms of
exercise
and I typically just do some gentle stretches kind of yin yoga or a starlet of
yoga I like to
practice a lot of meditation at this time as it's that introverted time it's
good that kind of mental
clarity and a good time for taking naps as well and I'm just treating it as a
like a nice little
holiday getting yourself some flowers or something anything like that make it
something to look
forward to because I know that the menstruation the menstrual cycle it's kind
of got this bit of
a bad rap really um so just really treating yourself indulging yourself at this
time
would be my advice here so that you feel well rested and replenished ready for
the for the month
ahead and then from here we come into our inner spring so this is when during
the follicular phase
that time after our bleed has finished our oestrogen levels are beginning to
rise and so
oestrogen actually enhances the release of serotonin and serotonin is a happy
hormone it's the happiness
hormone that makes us feel good so you might notice that during this time you
feel a lot better now
from what you were feeling probably last week when you were on your bleed time
and again it's a really
nice time for playfulness, creativity, so starting new projects maybe getting
together with friends
and kind of brainstorming new ideas that kind of energy and with the rise in
oestrogen we're becoming
a little bit more extroverted in our nature as well so we're starting to feel a
little bit more
sociable it's a good time for perhaps scheduling meeting friends maybe not
going on like a big
night out or anything like that not having a big family party but just feeling
a little bit more
social going to meet friends for coffee or what have you and really tapping
into that energy
and because our oestrogen is on the rise we can begin to increase the intensity
of our exercise
as well say as I mentioned that oestrogen with that protective effect on our
muscles we can begin
to increase our exercise perhaps towards the kind of the beginning of your foll
icular phase
doing more cardio-based exercises and then as oestrogen continues to rise
towards the
late end of your follicular phase this is when you can start to think about
incorporating a few
more kind of strength exercises as well okay so from here we roll into our
glorious inner
summer our ovulation so this window is your fertile window and this is when
oestrogen is really peaking
so oestrogen has a lot of impact on our body and in particular our brain so
oestrogen actually stimulates the verbal and social centres of the brain so this
is when your
communication levels are going to be at their highest so this is when your your
most dazzling
people will want to listen to what you have to say because you'll really feel
as if you're vocalizing
yourself well with that effect of oestrogen on your mind on your brain here so
it's a good time
for maybe having those slightly tricky conversations where you need to feel
a little bit braver um or having those kind of big parties those big social
gatherings because
you'll be at your best self here right now and because those oestrogen levels
are so high they'll
have that strong protective effect on our muscles as well so you'll probably be
feeling pretty strong
this is a time to really go for it with your with your workouts and with
whatever you're doing
so now yeah now is just the time to live your best life during your ovulation
you'll be feeling
at your best you'll be feeling your most attractive we even have oestrogen
receptors in our skin so
your skin will naturally be more glowy so this is um the time to really make
good use of all of your
inner power and give it to the rest of the world and show them what you're made
of really so go for
it during your ovulation on all that and then as we roll into our inner bottom
our luteal face
that peak of oestrogen is beginning to wait now so it's beginning to drop the
hormone levels
are falling once again so this is the time when we're going from being out
there super
extroverted in the world we're beginning to turn our focus our attention in
wards so beginning to
feel a little bit more introverted and with this in mind kind of the effect of
the hormones on
our brain on our minds it's a really good time for details so if you've got
some kind of boring
admin work that you've been putting off now is really the best time to do it
because you'll be
super uber focused on getting those details down a really good time for tying
up loose ends
finishing any projects off you might at the beginning of your luteal face feel
quite social
still after the kind of high of your summer but as it goes on you'll be
beginning to feel less
social less like you want to see people so it's a good time for really kind of
preparing yourself
putting those boundaries up saying no to things that you definitely know you
don't want to do
keep those boundaries strong at this time and think about it in terms of your
harvest time so
you're getting things in the cupboard you're kind of getting the cupboard nice
and full
you're preparing for the winter ahead your menstruation so that you can really
rest and replenish
slowing things down on all fronts whether it's work whether it's your social
side whether it's
your exercise whatever just slowing it all down decreasing the intensity and
just bringing yourself
back down once more so this is kind of a very brief whistle stop tour through
each of our main
phases of our cycle but I hope that you can begin to see how you can begin to
work with your cycle
a bit more plan your life around it so that you feel a little bit more in tune
with yourself
but how on earth do you get started with it all so tracking your cycle I would
recommend
beginning on the first day of your period so you can get you can get journals
with it in
or you can just write down if you've got a diary or anything like that you can
write it down in there
we've created and designed a specialised cycle tracker in the lunar sister
collective membership
area that you can download and print off each month and keep track of so what
you're keeping
track of in there is not just your bleed but anything at all that springs to
mind so
how you're feeling that day your thoughts kind of your mood your energy levels
your activity levels
what self-care practices you were doing anything at all that springs to mind so
and then over time
as you track each day going along you'll begin to notice patterns emerging and
you'll learn a lot
more about yourself actually so I've kind of discovered that in the first half
of my cycle I'm
not particularly hungry I typically have two meals a day and then in the second
half of my cycle I'm
just hungry all the time and I'm just going to eat all of the things and there
's other things that
are more subtle like I've noticed I really really hate baths during the first
half of my cycle I
just got there there's just the worst and then in the second half I'm like oh
yes I've allowed
you here for hours it's just glorious so it's all just little things like that
that you can pick
up on and I was chatting to a friend who also does a lot of cycle tracking work
and she was telling me
about a lady that she'd worked with who for one day of her cycle every month
she was just convinced
that her husband was trying to kill her and she just didn't know why and and it
turned out that
it was just on that particular day of her cycle she was just much more
sensitive to the speed of his
driving his driving hadn't changed throughout the month but it was something
going on in her
that she was just much more sensitive to it and was just convinced he was going
to try and kill her
but I think he wasn't so there's just all sorts of milk works that you can pick
up along the way
and as I say I prefer to do it on kind of pen and paper it's a really nice
thing to do towards the
end of the day I have a nice wind down activity before you go to bed and just
journaling it all
down but if you're more of an app person there are a number of apps that you
can download and I also
use a system called natural cycles so natural cycles you're given a thermometer
and you wake up
first thing in the morning and you measure your temperature just to kind of
track where you are
so your temperature fluctuates throughout your cycle as well so that just helps
to keep you on
track a little bit more especially if you're not quite sure what phase you're
in natural cycles
can help you because you just pop it down in your phone and it keeps track of
your temperature
throughout your cycle and then just before you ovulate your temperature drops
just a little
bit and then it goes through the roof and then you kind of know how I have ov
ulated and are now
in my luteal phase so those are just some helpful ideas to help you get started
with tracking your
cycle but begin on the first day of your period and that's just the easiest way
to get started with
it all and then of course we also have the lovely lunar sister collective so
lunar sister collective
is I think personally a really supportive environment so it's all geared up to
this idea of cyclical
living so we've got a mindful video library in there to support each phase of
your cycle so
tracking with your menstrual cycle or if you prefer to track with the moon we
've also got
lots of videos on that as I say we've got that downloadable tracker that you
can download and
print out each month and we've also got a bunch of cycle workbooks where you
can
work through each different phase of your cycle and really tap into the energy
at each phase
and we've also got a really nice community board as well for lovely supportive
women as well
so if you sign up we've got a free free day trial which is not easy me to say a
free
three-day trial so you can have a look around have a little nosy if you want to
check it out and see
what content we've got there just really nice self-care practices really to
help support you at each
phase of your cycle so that's lunar sister collective dot com and if you've
been interested in at all
what I've had to say this evening I hope you have there's a load of recommended
reading um loads
of books out there where you can really read more so if you love all this kind
of stuff I would
definitely recommend giving at least the vitties books a go um so her first
book was I'd put it
second hit but her first book was actually called woman code um and it's all
about her journey of
healing PCOS polycystic ovarian syndrome so that's what her first book is about
and then in the flow
is her second book and that's more about aligning every facet of your life um
in tune with your
period so from nutrition exercise parenting motherhood all of that kind of
stuff it's all in the flow
there and then for wild power that's kind of more of a I guess spiritual book
so it looks at
more of the energy patterns of each phase of your menstrual cycle
and then also well worth the read a little bit of a curveball here but how pill
changes everything
by dr sarah hill and if you're on the contraceptive pill or if you have
questions about the contraceptive
pill I would definitely definitely recommend this book um sarah just she's she
's quite funny it sounds
kind of a bit dry and a bit boring but she's got a really good sense of humor
and and makes you laugh
out loud but it just makes you realise um how the pill really does impact every
every aspect
um of your life um from your partner that you choose to how you're feeling on a
given day
so well worth a read if you're if you're on the pill and then obviously a
lovely unisister
collector dot com lots of free content on there as well as well as our
membership area so those
are my recommended reads and I can send this um slide show to you guys if you
want it afterwards
as well so that you can have that to hand but that is all for me sorry that was
a bit of a whistle
stop tour um I hope that was all clear if anyone has any questions I am here
for you
thank you so much thank you so much that was that was awesome um I loved it and
I definitely
learned some things I see georgia's face as well like it's you smiling and so
yeah you know what
like I recently I never used to really be into my body or anything like that
and recently I talked
to daily I'm feeling and it's nice to hear what you've got to say because feel
like it's within
that process I'm doing that push the lens of it you know it's nice that
actually you have
also a moment of our body and champions waiting for our body from them to face
it
over my area if you want to be there you have to feel it but actually we should
learn how to deal
with all the feelings not the end but do you want to tell us now yeah I don't
get that
yeah yeah and I think and I think that is something that we can bring into what
we do as well because
we sort of go through the month planning things and and georgia and I always
discuss sort of the moon
and different cycles and stuff and what's going on with each other and support
each other for you
that but I think maybe even planning what we're doing as a community and like
pointing ourselves
towards it and that's what we need don't want to bring it into different
communities and start
the conversation and point ourselves towards ourselves you know constantly
because that's what
we've been conditioned out of doing isn't it yeah and I think it's so nice that
you've got a community
of women as well because I don't feel like we do have these opportunities to
chat about it with
with other women and kind of share experiences I know when I first started
talking to my best friend
about periods she was like oh finally someone to talk to her about it all and
she got quite
excited um yeah and on the whole I don't think uh yeah I don't feel we have
these these opportunities
to share and and so yeah I hope this was useful for you and and you can kind of
just just give yourself
give yourself a break I would say just stop trying to live up to the
expectation that society
um puts on us and just think you know what I'm on my period I just want to lie
down and the rest of
the world is going to have to be okay with that yeah exactly I feel a no
worries now absolutely
so does anybody else have any questions or anything they want to say ladies
great
can I say questions hello Amy that was amazing thank you um I've always tracked
my period and then
now I'm heavily pregnant do you have any advice for like you know getting back
into the period
cycle if that makes sense like I'm scared that the hormones are gonna drop and
I'm just gonna like
I do I don't know the advice of the bar yes like a first period again I don't
know
yeah well congratulations I imagine it will probably take your hormones um a
little while to settle
down again um after you've given birth so I would definitely recommend um
getting back on
all of it as as soon as you come on to your your first bleed really um I mean
it might take a little
while to settle down there might be a few kind of cycles but just just go with
it I would say I
would recommend um and that book that I mentioned that in the flow book that
might be worth a read
as well because she kind of talks about getting back on track um with your
cycle as well by Lisa
Viti that that would be a good read for you um but yeah just just start as soon
as you can um work
with well I like natural cycles are a bit biased um but I would say work with
something like natural
cycles where you can track your temperature as well because um that just helps
to keep it a
little bit more accurate they also do these strips um that measure luteinizing
hormone as well and
you just we on them and they they give you kind of more of an accurate reading
where you are in
your cycle as well so that might be able that might be helpful for you for kind
of working out where
you are again okay thank you so I'm a therapist it's like a therapist and I had
a client once he was
like pregnant he was heavily pregnant she was really struggling with not having
that not having
that normal cycle but in her life just in general and so she started sort of
just sort of aligning
yourself or sort of using the moon phases to kind of think about where she was
in the month and
and yeah I thought that was really nice to you know look to the the next you
know go out with
a bit from yourself I suppose because she didn't have that bodily thing going
on yeah and the moon
is really useful um if if you don't have a period or if if you're on the
contraceptive pill because
you're not having a true period it it stops you from ovulating um so then I
would recommend
tracking with the moon rather than your cycle um but as I I mentioned they all
kind of line up
very similar the kind of energies at each different time so if you are on the
contraceptive pill or if
you're not got a period at the moment or what have you then then track with the
moon instead be it
just helps you to look a little bit more grounded and more in tune with life I
find often the end I
wear them all the time yeah yeah sure thank you anybody else anyone else have
any questions
uh I think I think I just answered your question Emily I hope that was helpful
sorry I just saw
it in the chat there so yes I would I would say go with the moon um we there's
there's loads of
really cool moon apps that you can download we've just gone past the full moon
so
we're moving from that full moon period um into kind of the waning moon time so
we've gone from
high full energy dropping back down again now so so yeah definitely download a
few moon apps
we've got loads of um content on lunar system collective all about the moon as
well
thank you so much thank you so much Amy um so if anybody wants to sign up to
that they just go to
the website lunisysconnectivecollective.com
I think we'll find it also on in the boxes
so we're going to thank you sir okay thank you for having me to talk with you
share about it I'm sure we all know something very important that we can
no worries at all did did you have a question safe sorry I saw you yes sorry I
am I just wondered
because I mean this is the first time I've ever really spoken or looked into or
heard anything
about it I'm a terrible terrible woman no you're not alone I was like oh my god
that makes
so much sense and I'm really excited about it um because for years and years I
was just on a
on a contraceptive pill because doctors were like oh that's a nuisance get rid
of it get rid of
it it'll stop you know and I haven't been on it since I have my little in but I
do have
polycystic ovaries and I wondered if that as a condition medical thing um does
that affect it
at all or with your hormone levels do you just not how does it work yeah so I
have PCOS as well um
and which is kind of where I got involved with elisa bitty because she has PCOS
and her book woman
code is it really talks about how she healed herself um from PCOS I don't know
if you can ever
really heal yourself but how she like completely manages her symptoms now and
and she has a regular
cycle um so that's why I was drawn towards her so I would definitely recommend
giving that a read
um because since living more in alignment with my cycle because mine would come
once in a blue moon really like I get a period once every three or four five
months I don't even
know how often it was because it was just when it fancied it got really um so I
mean I have managed
to get mine back on track really through kind of diet exercise that kind of
thing even looking at
the moment I'm really I'm a bit of a geek sorry um I'm kind of really getting
into all the all the
chemicals and stuff all the kind of hormone disrupting stuff that's in our
environment like
all the kind of stuff that's in shampoo and body lotion all that stuff it kind
of all
it all plays with our hormonal system and all of that it sounds horrible and
scary when you first
start reading it but if you do it kind of step by step um would be my
recommendation so yes it might
sorry long long question um long answer sorry but um yeah I would definitely
just start um the next
time that your period comes along see how you get along with it just track your
cycle and um yeah
I would definitely say have a little look at your diet like even things like
knocking out caffeine
just made such a huge difference to me because it was I was I just couldn't
understand my deodorant
just didn't work for me I'll just sweat and sweat and sweat and sweat and then
I stopped drinking
caffeine and done done it was just fixed like that and then just all sorts of
other little things that
you can you can just knock out really um so I would just say get to know
yourself a little bit better
you can track you can track your moods track your food what you're eating um
really just
just start tracking I would say will be my recommendation and see what works
for you
give a Lisa Vitti's book a read um woman code definitely recommend that and yes
I hope that's
helpful um Sammy's written something um I really stuff with migraines when I'm
on my period the
doctor put me on the pill her advice was having four periods of years better
than 12 you have any
advice on how to cope or stop his headache um I'm afraid I can't really answer
that one because I
I'm not I'm not a specialist or a doctor in that area um but again I would
recommend just looking
at your whole your whole system so your your whole lifestyle really what you're
eating your
stress levels stress has such an impact on our hormonal system as well so
taking care to do all
that self-care and stuff but migraines are such a tricky business um I think
there is a bit of
research about migraines and oestrogen levels that might be interesting for you
to take a look at
um and I know there's stuff on kind of migraines and histamine intolerance as
well which might be
an interesting road to look down but I'm not a specialist by any means I'm just
very interested
in in well-being and wellness so um I'm sorry I can't give you any specific
advice there
um I have a question I don't know whether it's something that you'd
have an opinion on or whatever but I went for a hormone lady doctor um because
my cycles were
just getting more and more painful like before I was happy before the week
before my period so
that illiculate phase no that's not illiculate your phase yes that's um and she
gave me um like
a hormone replacement gel at Easter gel um yeah just wonder what your thoughts
are on on that do
you have any thoughts on it and on hRT um I know a lot of women find it very
useful around kind of
menopause and things it sounds almost as if you have um kind of I mean again it
's it's all very
individual to you is what I would say but when we do have um kind of symptoms
of pms it's typically
a sign that something is out of balance somewhere so whether it's typically I
think it is too much
oestrogen um but so I'm not sure quite why she would give you a hormone hRT um
because that would
elevate your oestrogen levels even further um so I know things like having a lot
of fiber in your
diet is really good for removing excess oestrogen and that might help to reduce
symptoms of pms kind
of like um that bloating that painfulness kind of really sore nipples that kind
of stuff because
all a sign of like really high oestrogen and things like that so um yeah I would
I would perhaps
recommend looking at um uh kind of your more beauty of really honing in on that
um and yeah looking at things that help to get rid of excess oestrogen or if
there's um anything
that's out of balance in another system like if you're eating too much sugar
and your insulin levels
are too high this other system over here has to compensate for it so again it's
it's looking at
the whole picture really um I mean if if the gel worked for you then that's
that's great um but yeah
I would always kind of recommend looking at the whole picture getting to know
yourself getting
to know what works for you um and what has an effect on you thank you no that's
thank you
that's informative and I yeah I was curious about that about the about having
more oestrogen versus
having less so yeah thank you no worries I think it's a tricky area because um
a lot of
I don't know if it was a GP you saw or a specialist or anything yeah but I don
't think gps get um
like specialised training for kind of women's issues unless there are
specialists in that area
they just they don't know about it at the moment unfortunately and I know there
's a lot of work
kind of going into it now more so especially with kind of well I want to say
endometriosis but
I think it still takes women over five years to get a proper diagnosis on that
but there's a lot
more work going into menopause training for gps at the moment so the tide is
turning um but it's
taking a long for a long long time to get there unfortunately so we have to do
all the work ourselves
in the meantime which is very boring any more questions anyone else the
question
okay um well I think that's us coming to the end then isn't it um let me see
then thank you again
so much um aimee that was that was great and I'm sure and we'll all be talking
about it in the chat
afterwards uh thank you for having me it was so yeah it was so unique to me to
connect with and
yeah you're really lovely to listen to so we really appreciate you coming in
talking to us thank you
so much thank you well if anyone has any questions um you can always drop me a
line um I'm on Instagram
@unissistercollective and then my email is just any@unissistercollective.com so
if there's anything
you think of in the middle of the night you want to ask me then you can just
drop me a line I don't mind
oh thank you and we will post um obviously we'll upload this and we'll post all
the links in our
chat and stuff anyway so anyone can just call me if you want to speak to you
definitely thank you
enjoy the rest I'm doing thank you everyone yes and take care nice to meet you
all
see you all soon bye thank you bye thank you